A Guide to the Papers of The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry 1934-2001
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Dr. Barbara Brodie Papers 1955-1975, 1 box, .4 linear feet
  - School of Nursing History
    - Rockingham Memorial Hospital 1970 (Box-folder 001-032)
      Re: Letter sent with history.
    - Shenandoah College, Winchester, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-033)
      Re: Letter sent with history of AD nursing program.
    - St. Elizabeth's Hospital, Richmond, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-034)
      Re: Typed history, 1912-1957.
    - St. Luke's Hospital, Richmond 1970-1975 (Box-folder 001-035)
      Re: Newsletter, catalog, and blooklet.
    - St. Phillip 1958 (Box-folder 001-036)
      Re: Typed history: 1920-1958.
    - Thomas Nelson Community College, Hampton, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-037)
      Re: Loose pages from catalog.
    - Tidewater Community College [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-038)
    - Winchester Memorial Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-039)
      Re: Typed history 1902-1958.
    - Buchanan County School of P.N. 1967 (Box-folder 001-0)
      Re: Brief handwritten history: 1966-67.
  - Series 2: School of Practical Nursing History
    - Clinch Valley Clinic Hospital, Richlands, Va. 1968 (Box-folder 001-041)
      Re: Letter & typed history, 1945-1965.
    - Culpeper Memorial Hospital School of P.n> 1968 (Box-folder 001-042)
      Re: Handwritten history: 1957-1968
    - Danville Technical Institute and Memorial Hospital 1967 (Box-folder 001-043)
      Re: Letter, brief typed history, 1952-1966, & booklet.
    - Dewitt Army Hospital, Ft. Belvior, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-044)
      Re: Typed history of clinical specialist course and Walter Reed course.
    - Dixie Hospital, Hampton City School 1967 (Box-folder 001-045)
      Re: Typed history; 1951-1959.
    - Fairfax County, School of P.N. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-046)
      Re: Brief typed history: 1960-1966.
    - Greensville Memorial Hospital, Emporia, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-047)
      Re: Typed history: 1967
    - Louise OBICI Memorial Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-048)
      Re:Typed history, 1957-1967.
    - Martinsville General Hospital, Henry County School 1967 (Box-folder 001-059)
      Re: Typed history; 1964 - 1967.
    - Mary Washington Hosp/Frederickburg, Stafford County Public Schools [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-050)
      Re: Typed history.
    - Martha Jefferson Hospital, Charlottesville, Va. 1955-1968 (Box-folder 001-051)
      Re: Typed history & statistical summary.
    - Medical College of Va. Hospital School of P.N. 1958 (Box-folder 001-052)
      Re: Typed history: 1946-1958.
    - Northampton-Accomack Memorial Hospital 1955 (Box-folder 001-053)
      Re:Brief typed history of white & black students.
    - New River Vocational Technical School, Pulaski [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-054)
      Re: Typed history: 1960-1966.
    - Norfolk City Schools, Leigh Memorial Hospital 1968 (Box-folder 001-055)
      Re: Typed history: 1946-1968.
    - Norfolk General Hospital 1968 (Box-folder 001-056)
      Re: Footnotes history, 1947-1967.
    - Porstmouth School of P.N. 1967 (Box-folder 001-057)
      Re: Typed history: 1967-1968.
    - Roanoke County Educational Center 1967 (Box-folder 001-058)
      Re: Letter with statistics 1963-67.
    - Southampton Memorial Hospital 1963-1968 (Box-folder 001-059)
      Re: Scrapbook history, 1963-1968.
    - Southside Community Hospital, Farmville, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-060)
      Re: Letter & brochure.
    - Smyth County School of P.N. 1967 (Box-folder 001-061)
      Re: Leter with brief history.
    - Stonewall Jackson Hospital, Lexington, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-062)
      Re: Brief typed history: 1964-1966.
    - (Box-folder 001-063)
    - Tripllet Business & Technical Institute, Mt. Jackson, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-064)
      Re: Typed letter with history & handbook.
    - University of Va. Hospital School of P.N. & Jackson P. Burey High School 1951-1968 (Box-folder 001-065)
      Re: Typed history: 1951-1957.
    - Winchester Memorial Hospital School of P.N. 1967 (Box-folder 001-066)
      Re: Letter detailing history.
- Rose Marie Chioni Papers 1940-1967, 3 boxes, 1.25 linear feet
  Dr. Rose Marie Chioni, a native of LaSalle, Illinois, received her nursing diploma from St. Francis Hospital School of Nursing in Peoria, Illinois, in 1953. She graduated from the University of Minnesota in 1956 with a B.S.N.Ed., received her M.A. degree in 1958 from the University of Chicago, and was awarded a Ph.D. degree from Ohio State University in 1964. On December 31, 1988, Dr. Chioni resumed a faculty role at the University of Virginia School of Nursing after fourteen years as Dean and Sadie Heath Cabaniss Professor of Nursing. Under her progressive leadership Virginia's first doctoral program in nursing was begun. She retired in May 1995.
  This collection consists of personal and professional papers, presentations, and published articles focusing primarily on professional issues in nursing and nursing education, on both the state and national levels. The bulk of the material dates from 1963 to 1994. The Rose Marie Chioni Papers have been arranged chronologically within topical categories: 1950-1994.
  - Box 1: Personal Materials and Speeches
    - Awards, Curriculum Vitae, and Biographical Sketches (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Current research activity, 1970-1981; AACN plaque; paid consulting activities; retirement dinner program; Oscar and Ruth Lanford Award.
    - Record of Ward Teaching and Practice (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Clinical assignments, activities, skills learned and teaching done as student nurse in diploma program.
    - Case Studies (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Pharmacology class, nursing care study on woman with cervical cancer and anemia in last months of life, pediatric case study on a 5-year old male with pyloric stenosis.
    - Nursing Arts Notebook (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Review of textbook chapters.
    - Personal Materials I (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Ph.D. preliminary examination paper, nursing shortage papers, nurse-physician collaboration paper.
    - Personal Materials II (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: University of Wisconsin papers and published articles, reprints from journals, memoranda, newspaper clippings.
    - Personal Materials III (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: University of Wisconsin: Task Force reports, evaluation of new BSN curriculum, peer evaluation of educational programs, role expectations of professional nurse practitioners.
    - Personal Materials IV (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Correspondence from Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Society of Professional Nurses; Nursing Alumni Newsletters, Division of Nursing Newsletters, AACN Brochures.
    - Dissertation Proposal (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: A Study of the Relationships between the Effectiveness of Predicted Success and Reported Success in One Collegiate Nursing Education Program.
    - Speeches I (Box-folder 001-010)
      Virginia Association for Continuing Education in the Health Professions; NLN speeches by Margaret E. Walsh; "Consumerism: Its Impact on America's Health Professionals"; "Summary of Remarks on 'The Politics of Health' by Herman Somers at National League for Nursing Convention, Anaheim, CA,"; Nurses' Role in Patient Rights; A Statement of Concern about Associate and Baccalaureate Degree Programs for Nurses that have No Major in Nursing; Changing Student Relationships: Institution and Administration.
    - Speeches II (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: NLN Update Speech, Nursing Education for the Future: Position Paper; Wayne State University Nursing Convocation, AACN Workshop: Grants for Nursing Education and Research - "Planning the Project"; First Annual Conference - Health Occupations Educators and Supervisors; Keys to Professional Nursing: Research, Leadership, Practice; Nursing Education in the 80s; The State of the Art in Academic Nursing. A CEU Certificate.
    - Speeches III (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Press statement re: Ph.D. in Nursing; Cultural View of Final Stages of Life; Brochure - Conference on Legal Controversies in Nursing (DC, MD, & VA); Recruitment, Retention, & Rewards for Faculty; Council on Collegiate Education for Nursing; Where is Nursing Going...?; The Relationship Between Predicted and Reported Success in One Collegiate Nursing Program; VNA Annual Convention.
    - Speeches IV (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: Barriers to Teaching & Learning; Holistic Nursing -- The New Profession; Nursing Practice at the Bedside: Strategies for the Eighties.
    - Speeches V (Box-folder 001-014)
      Re: Wellness, What is It?; Leadership: Quest for Excellence; Charting the Future for Nursing Research, Nursing Education and Nursing Practice; Longing to Find our Ultimate Worth in Who We Are Rather than What We Do; Nothing Has Changed; Licensure: What is It?; Licensure for the Future.
  - Box 2: Publications, Articles, and State-level Committees 1970-1990
    - Published Articles I (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: "Tomorrow's Nurse Practitioners", Nursing Outlook, February, 1970. "Preparing Tomorrow's Nurse Practitioners", Nursing Outlook, October, 1970. (Journals and article reprints); "Nursing Education for the Future: A Position Paper" (undated).
    - Publications II (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Book chapters and supporting documents.
    - Publications III (Research Articles) (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Three drafts of article "Emergency Nursing Education: A Proposal for Curricular Change".
    - Publications IV - (Continuation of Folder 3) (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Drafts and correspondence related to article, "Emergency Nursing Education: A Proposal for Curricular Change".
    - Review and Update of Criteria to Estimate Future Requirements for Nursing Personnel - for DHHS (Division of Nursing) (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Correspondence, memoranda, and criteria for review sent to members of expert panel to review and update the criteria; summary tables; group conclusions.
    - Nurse Shortage: Dean Chioni's Study I (Box-folder 002-006)
    - Nurse Shortage - Dean's Study II (Box-folder 002-007)
      Re: Articles and correspondence.
    - Nurse Shortage - Governor's Study Commission I (Box-folder 002-008)
    - Nurse Shortage - Governor's Commission Study - II (Box-folder 002-009)
  - Box 3: University of Virginia Work & Correspondence, and National-level Collaboratives 1981-1988
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: Board of Regents of University of Georgia; University of Pittsburgh; Virginia House of Delegates; Kentucky Council on Higher Education; Virginia Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; Sigma Theta Tau, Inc., Beta Kappa Chapter; O. A Thorrup, Associate Dean, University of Virginia; Lucy Blanton; Nurses Corporation of America; North Carolina Biotechnology Center; Marion B. Peavey, Vice President for Development, University of Virginia; Jefferson Area Board for Aging; Betty Johnson, Acting Associate Dean for Community Service, University of Virginia; Barbara Graham; Thomas Jackson, Vice President/Provost, University of Virginia; Laurel Archers Copp, Journal of Professional Nursing; Patricia Moccia, American Academy of Nursing; University of Colorado Health Sciences Center.
    - Banding Ceremonies - Programs and Awards Information (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Correspondence, Nine programs, Beverly Reamy Howard Scholarship fund information; Denise Kaye Netherland Memorial Nursing Scholarship fund and related correspondence.
    - Nurse Specialist (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Burn, Trauma, and Emergency Medicine proposal and correspondence.
    - Report of the Graduate medical Education National Advisory Committees to the Secretary, DHHS 1980 (Box-folder 003-004)
    - The Educational "Pipeline" in Nursing 1987 (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: AACN Paper by Kenneth C. Green.
    - Employment of UVA Graduates (Box-folder 003-006)
      "Factors Affecting Employment of Graduates of the University of Virginia School of Nursing from 1978-1980", a paper; Summary of previous study; Chioni, cont'd. Abstract of study; Results of Employment Survey of Fourth Year UVA Nursing Students; "Supply and Demand Relations and the Shortage of Nurses", Johnson and Vaughn.
    - Plans for the Year 2000 (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: Plan for the Year 2000 - statement as Supplement to the University of Virginia Alumni News; School of Nursing Mission and Goals Statement; Draft of AACN Position Statement for 21st Century.
    - Minutes/Faculty Memos (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Internal Management Concerns of School of Nursing Minutes, Memoranda, Correspondence Re: Organizational Structure and Management.
    - Medical Center Nursing Resource Review Task Force Committee Meeting I (Minutes) (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Department of Nursing Profile, Minutes, Correspondence.
    - Medical Center Nursing Resource Review Task Force II (Documents) (Box-folder 003-010)
      Re: Correspondence; Report - bound; Recommendations; Progress Reports; News Clippings; Enrollment Figures for School of Nursing for 1987-1988; One AHA publication on the Nursing Shortage: "Surviving the Nursing Shortage: Strategies for Recruitment and Retention of Hospital Nurses"; Interim Report; Memoranda.
    - Medical Center Nursing Review Task Force Committee Meeting III (Minutes) (Box-folder 003-011)
      Re: Minutes, and Report on Rush-Presbyterian-St. Luke's Model for Nursing Practice and Education; Memoranda, Correspondence, Draft Recommendations.
    - Newspaper Articles (Box-folder 003-012)
      Re: Nursing Shortage; School of Nursing Enrollment; Dean Chioni.
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 003-013)
      Re: Memo from Frances Butler, expense report for NLN meeting; Activity Report of Individual Faculty member; Aerial view of UVA grounds (2 photos); Photos and flier for "Family and Community Empowerment Workshop", New Hope Baptist Church, Esmont, VA.
- CNHI: Annie Laurie Crawford Papers 1934-1987, 3 boxes, 1.25 linear feet
  This collection consists primarily of publications, presentations, memos, conference reports, and correspondence by Annie Laurie Crawford. These include articles written for professional journals and reports of staff development and consultation activities conducted by Crawford, such as workshops, seminars, institutes and programs for psychiatric aides, LPN's, and RNs. The correspondence includes Crawford's letters to journal editors, communication with health institutions related to psychiatric nursing consulting work, and correspondence with state nurses' associations. The collection also contains pamphlets and articles collected by Crawford, mostly related to mental health and psychiatric nursing, and certificates and awards presented to her over the course of her career. The materials range in date from the 1940s to the 1980s, and represent an overview of Crawford's career and interests rather than an extensive collection of her work.
  This series has been arranged into four chronological series. Series 1: Publications, presentations, and memos by Crawford, Series 2: Crawford Correspondence 91942-1984), Series 3: Notes, papers, articles, and news clippings collected by Crawford (1941-1980), Series 4: Certificates and Awards.
  - Series 1: Publications, presentations, and memos by Crawford, Series 2: Crawford Correspondence 91942-1984), Series 3: Notes, papers, articles, and news clippings collected by Crawford (1941-1980)
    - Correspondence related to acquisition of the Crawford (Box-folder 001-00A)
    - Publications, presentations, memos by Crawford (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Psychiatry: a nursing essential; The place of metal hygiene in a health program; The challenge of psychiatric nursing; Alabama State Nurses' Association recruitment for Schools of Nursing; Organizing the Nursing Department to serve the Patients.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: ASNA annual convention report; Psychiatric Nursing-Dynamic Pattern 1951; Issues related to nursing shortage: report to Alabama State Headquarters; Nurses vs. Doctor; An unresolved question; "Annie Laurie Day"; Role of identification in learning: seminar presentation; Draft of paper presented to South Carolina Nurses' Association annual convention.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Mental health and psychiatric nursing in Florida: status report; The public health nurse in after care of psychiatric patients; The function of public health nursing in the rehabilitation process; The nursing survey.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: The Joint Commission report on mental illness and health: implications for nursing administration; Mental health psychiatric nursing staff development; Mental health and psychiatric nursing project; South Carolina League Nursing convention; Conference report of state consultants in mental health and psychiatric nursing; Mental health today.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Utilization of the practical nurse in mental health; Summary of responses to request; Responsibility for staff development; York native son championed cause of independence; Preparing auxiliary personnel to give nursing care to the geriatric patient.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: The challenge of psychiatric nursing; The Joint Commission Report on mental illness and health: implications for nursing administration; The work and training of technical and vocational personnel in psychiatric nursing; Regional Planning for continuing education in psychiatric nursing; Teaching psychiatric nursing.
    - Crawford Correspondence 1942-1953 (Box-folder 001-007)
    - Crawford Correspondence 1953-1956 (Box-folder 001-008)
    - Crawford Correspondence 1956-1974 (Box-folder 001-009)
    - Crawford Correspondence 1978-1984 (Box-folder 001-010)
    - Notes, papers, articles, and news clippings collected by Crawford (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: Post-War reform in mental nursing; History repeats itself; The nurse of the future; Mental health progress; Description of prospective project; University of Minnesota School of Nursing seminar presentation; Some anthropological aspects of nursing; Curriculum outline.
    - (Continued from Folder 11) (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Minnesota department of public welfare announces a limited number of stipends for advanced study in Psychiatric Nursing; Nursing Services; Sharp turn in psychiatric; Can nurses be group therapists; Courage to turn your back on a drowning man; Psychiatric nurse in outpatient clinic; Mental health briefs.
    - (Continued from Folder 11) (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: National Commission for the study of Nursing and Nursing education; Nursing research report; The extended role of the nurse in an occupational mental health program; Professional ethics; Functions of Professional ethics; International council of nurses Code of Ethics; First National conference on classification of nursing diagnoses; Evaluation sheet for milieu therapy workshop.
    - (Continued from Folder 11) (Box-folder 001-0)
      Re: What is mental health; General outline for organization of public relations program in state and district Nurses' Association; Workshop evaluation sheet, Manuscript review questions.
    - Notes, papers, articles, and news clippings collected by Crawford (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Virginia's psychiatric care programs draw praise; Dr. Mead warns against national disease menace; Four hundred nurses expected here today for state convention, campaign to enroll nurses intensified; Nurse recruits need stressed; Kentucky nurses study public relations techniques; St. Peter Tests new nurse training plan; The inebriate in the emergency room; It's 'Goodbye VU, Hello, Virginia' for Annie Laurie; Nurse Annie Laurie Crawford remembers the last days of Thomas Wolfe; Aging a concern for all generations.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Retarded adults learning community living skills; Panel on aging to consider project funds; The elderly are people not problems; Herb gardens reward in many ways; Donation caps nurse's career; Eastern state's goodie cart is therapy on wheels.
    - Continued from Folder 1 (Box-folder 001-0)
      Re: Health nurses need to be counselors; Studies show environment may influence addictions; Elderly may occupy complex in February.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: The training of a nurse; A working definition of anxiety; The Michigan Nurse; Mental Health Progress.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Nursing Forum; Application for training grant; Nursing digest.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: News letter from University of Washington Nursing Alumni; The final guardians; A demonstration of potential public health nursing contributions to community mental health care.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Clinical experts; The southeastern hospital conference; Nursing personnel for mental health programs; Mental health training and research in the southern states; Examining psychiatric nursing skills.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Practical psychiatric nursing-report of a pilot training and evaluation project for psychiatric aides; Utilization of nursing personnel-a bibliographical survey.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: The teaching of psychiatric-mental health nursing in the basic professional nursing program; The problem: psychiatric in-patient units in general hospitals; Tennessee Nurses' Association 60th annual convention; In-service training for Mental health programs.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: Psychiatric nursing-a developmental statement for study and reaction; A critical research report from the Appalachian research collective; Image; the Journal of nursing administration.
    - (Continued from Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-0)
      Re: World health magazine; Eastern state hospital problem oriented record instruction manual.
  - Series 3 continued and Series 4: Certificates and Awards
    - Notes, papers, articles, and news clippings collected by Crawford (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: ANA ethnic minority fellowship program; Journal of psychosocial nursing and mental health services; Association of Virginia Antiquities.
    - Crawford Awards and Recognitions (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Resolution of appreciation of Crawford by Minnesota Nurses Association; Recognition of Crawford's work by Choctaw tribe of North, American Indians; Personalities of the South; Admission to the American Academy of Nursing; The distinguished contribution to psychiatric and mental health nursing awards; Recognized by American Nurses' Foundation; Recognized by Sigma Theta Tau International honor Society of Nursing.
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 003-0)
      Re: ANA guidelines; The Minnesota registered nurse; First commencement exercise of Minnesota department of public welfare School of Practical Psychiatric Nursing; The Florence Nightingale Pledge.
- CNHI: Kathryn Jaquette Papers 1969-1974, 3 boxes, 1.25 linear feet